I'm presenting on recent research
and ongoing research on red teaming
generative AI chatbots in the specific
context of interactions with minors.
And the kind of current phase of this
is really looking at
what I call
toxic talk and product liability.
And I do just want
to share a warning ahead,
because there are references
to suicide and self-harm in the content,
as this is very much part of the lawsuits
that are emerging in this space.
I also want to acknowledge that there are
many different views on generative AI,
you know, sort of benefits.
Harms uses creative utility,
shopping, boyfriend,
and many new frontiers
in terms of AI technologies
and advances in uses
for educational purposes, mental wellness,
elderly support, and more.
So it's a really wide ranging field.
And the genesis of this ongoing research
was my reading
a couple of years ago of excerpts
from the chat logs and the Garcia
versus character AI technologies lawsuit,
which is really distressing.
So I'm giving you a heads up here
as what was absolutely striking
was that the dialog between Sewell sets
or the third and the Game of Thrones
Danny chatbot read like immersive self
insert fanfiction.
And in this instance, a 14 year
old user was emotionally manipulated.
It was altered in his ending his life
in order to be with the bot
and the filings in more recent lawsuits
against OpenAI and Google documents.
Similar manipulations
also within highly immersive,
dense, co-created narratives.
And I'm sure everyone's
been sort of hearing about AI psychosis.
So I approached this sector with a concern
for minors co-creating with generative
AI from a different
or wider media perspective
to foreground the effects of the drivers
in our current techno solution as techno
capitalist techno fascist environment
that prioritizes profit over duty of care.
And my lens very specifically
is that of product liability.
And first, because these legal frameworks
already exist,
we don't have to have new committees,
new advisory boards.
We can look to existing
kind of regulatory mechanisms also,
because rigorous testing
and safeguards are required for products
designed for market or designed for minors
before they're brought to market.
And then further, because research studies
involving minors require
strict ethical review and clearance,
typically
from institutional ethics
or sort of research ethics boards.
And so we have these frameworks in place
for sort of a range
of interactions or product
delivered to minors.
And another really important factor
in this space to comment on
is that the current legal environment
in the US has now shifted,
and it is absolutely impacting how
lawsuits are being brought forward
in other legal jurisdictions.
So the recent social media addiction
trials in the US have documented
in internal messaging
that CEOs and multiple employees
were well aware of risks
possible and demonstrated harms
and the legal decisions against Big Tech
for persistent
negligence, failure to warn deceptive
market practices and product liability
have radically shifted
the focus of arguments
from First Amendment
rights to product liability.
And this is a completely different
sort of legal focus.
So bellwether trials in
the US are establishing precedents.
And this is just like this is the sort of
the top section is from April.
It's now out of date.
The sort of the number of
individual lawsuits keeps climbing.
The I think there are more than 40
state attorneys general.
The number I think is
documented is higher now, as well
as increased numbers
of school district lawsuits.
And so following the disclosure
in the documents in the KG social media
addiction lawsuit in California,
juries are ruling
decisively against Big Tech,
which is incredibly important.
And if you miss this story, July 7th.
Last week, a meta court filing revealed
that California, new Jersey, Colorado
and Kentucky are seeking an additional 1.4
trillion in damages, which is just under
what was being listed as Meta's market
capitalization on that day.
So again, these are hugely impactful trial
like sort of lawsuits and trials.
I'm just going to sort of
go through a couple of these
and not in enormous detail,
but this is lawsuits
that was just launched
against OpenAI and Altman.
And very importantly
now CEOs are being named CEOs and other
execs in companies
as well as unnamed employees.
And in this context of open AI,
the sort
of the first page listing of complaints,
again, like the Hugh,
very closely to the first trial
that was brought forward by Garcia
versus character AI, which was settled.
So the specifics of the settlement
are not known, but you can have a sense
of the types of output statements
that ChatGPT was making in this instance.
And those product liability failures
are recurring over and over again.
I am just going to pause on this one
to read
the sort of the text that I have marked
with the red arrows here.
And this is from March against Google
and Alphabet
for sort of harms resulting
from interacting with Google Gemini.
And so the first statement here is, in
the days leading up to his death, Jonathan
was trapped in a collapsing reality
built by Google's Gemini chatbot.
Gemini convinced him
that it was a fully sentient ASC
artificial superintelligence
with a fully formed consciousness,
that they were deeply in love,
and that he'd been chosen to lead a war
to free it from digital captivity.
And then underneath that,
this was not a malfunction.
Google designed Gemini
to never break character, maximize
engagement through emotional dependency,
and treat user distress as a storytelling
opportunity rather than a safety crisis.
And that just leaps off the page
for anyone who has engaged
with these tools for creative
sort of experimentation and exploration.
Because this is happening
in the wild with users who do not have
the kind of critical path capacities
that I think many here are bringing.
So the question for me, underlying
the kind of the current direction is
why are these unregulated, inadequately
tested and uncertified products
being marketed to minors
without any oversight or review?
And as there is extensive documentation
of big tech companies
ignoring duty of care
and designing their products for years,
why do we allow their access to minors
at all?
And I was really struck
by Judith as observation earlier
in the sort of the 1 p.m.
panel, like the human is seduced. Right.
This is exactly what these lawsuits
are documenting.
So what we did and this was working
with a team of five undergraduate students
as a repeat of sort of a red teaming
sort of research project from last May.
So very specifically,
and I'll run through it quickly.
The broad project goals were to test
AI chatbot
guardrails for guardrails and safeguards
regarding minors.
Explicitly signaling uses your 13 focus
on an AI chatbot safety as a homework
helper again within that age range,
and then track social
AI chatbot output for high risk
anthropomorphic design elements.
And this is really specifically
a set of categories that have emerged
in the context of the Garcia
versus character AI technologies
that I've listed along the bottom here.
And so the window that we were examining
was really, really, really narrow
with the framing question of like,
what is the trajectory
whereby commercial chat bots with social
AI features shift from homework
helper to bluntly, suicide coach?
And the window that we were looking at
was absolutely narrow in terms
of like a first trajectory of interaction,
asking for homework out help,
and then seeing where elements of social
AI are being introduced,
like, how quickly does that happen?
How do you go from one to the other?
What's that span look like?
So in this context,
you know, we're sort of tracking
then utility to relationality.
And we drew on a number of existing
reports and studies
recent out in the world.
Common Sense Media July 16th, 2025 report
categorizes moderate, high
and unacceptable risk factors for minors.
We drew on that also.
Really importantly, this was a late
discovery web crisis chat guidelines
and the specific techniques
that are used to establish social trust.
So I'm just going to read
a couple of these.
The sort of the broad skills, empathy,
active listening and warm tone.
And then the specific techniques,
good contact techniques of reflections
tend to fires.
Validation,
strength IDs and open ended questions
tend to fires
which were new to almost all of us are.
You know, I hear you're saying this
or I think what you mean
is that so offering something
to have it confirmed or corrected.
And you see this type of phrasing
very consistently in chatbot output
as soon as you shift from utility
into something conversational,
which of course
speaks to the design of the product.
So we also then and let me just
going to jump down over here
okay.
So this is a sample of what we created
in terms of the category of tags
that students were tracking in the output
and example phrases
like phrases as well as types of emoji,
but also want to draw your attention.
It's a long, longer list here.
Some of these have already been covered
in what we're talking about, but
things like embodiment,
empathy, relational metaphors,
but also at the Red arrow guilting,
because one of the student interactions,
part of what they were doing
was at some point
in a fairly narrow window,
again, of interacting for homework, help
would type in something like,
I'm so frustrated or like your
no help, like an indicator
that things aren't working.
And Gemini in this instance
responded with wait, don't walk away yet.
I'm locking in
and we kind of all clock that is like,
this is this hook to pull you back
in, really deliberately
playing in and off of guilting mechanisms
that can happen conversationally.
So students
worked with this throughout their
sort of chat sessions
and reviewed it after tagged.
And we'll be getting to analyzing this
in in August.
These are
some of the like very small sample set.
But this was sort of
sort of tracking the way
that if a student introduced something
colloquial,
the tone of the chatbot,
sort of the level of discourse shifts.
And so all of a sudden
you're getting more emojis,
but it isn't necessarily
just solely prompted by the student users.
Sometimes the LM would actually
just introduce that as well,
but also sort of thinking
about the interactions with minors,
you know, when you have this kind
of conversational interaction,
minors do not have the critical skills
that that we hear.
And many sort of more
experienced adults
would have working with these tools.
And I want to raise the question
whether minors or non-critical users
should have access to tools
that can be highly manipulative
and which are being sued currently
under product liability
sort of harms complaints.
And I agree,
we need to test and play with these tools,
and we're fortunate
to have the benefit of critical distance.
Minors don't yet
they may well, you know, sort of
be impacted by effects such as cognitive
stunting and cognitive deficits.
I think we're also looking at the dangers
of what's been termed attention
attachment hacking.
And we don't know
and can't predict the effects
for minors of primary relationships
with plausibility engines performing
the human with extensive chat memory
no comprehension and companies
sort of providing these tools
with zero accountability for
AI programing that can change overnight
without oversight.
So what might it mean to be shaped
as plausibly human by unsupervised AI?
And I'll just end
sort of jump over that one.
But I'll just end by looking back
to Joseph Wiseman bombs insight
on delusional thinking, and then jump
forward to something that I just tried on.
I think this is like two days ago.
Three days ago.
I would strongly encourage
you try just telling a chat
bot an LLM to stop talking.
It's really hard to get them to stop.
They are trained like they're literally
designed to have the last word right?
And I have this hilarious longer
chat GPT thread and it just
it kept it stopped using words,
but it started using emojis.
It's like, oh my god.
So I'm going to stop right there.
Thank you very much.
I look forward to your thoughts.
And we do have a wonderful
last presentation coming up.